[MUSIC]
效果量
In this lecture we'll talk about the concept of effect sizes.
這一講是效果量的概念入門
I'll explain what they're good for, how you can use them, and
我會說明善用效果量的好處，使用的方式
why you should report them.
還有應該報告效果量的理由
And in the next lectures, we'll dive into more detail in two families of effect
後續兩講介紹兩大類效果量
sizes, Cohen's d and correlations.
Cohen's d與相關係數
Now there are some people who think that effect sizes are in
在報告中呈現效果量已經是許多研究者的共識
essence the main thing that we're interested in when we perform a study.
There might be a lot of attention to the specific level of the p value, but
過去論文的寫作與閱讀特別注意p值的呈現
Cohen was one of the first to point out the importance of
而Cohen為代表的學者首先指出
effect sizes in the scientific literature, and he says this is basically the main
在科學文獻裡呈現效果量的重要性
thing that you want to know, the primary product of a researching crew.
更指出這應該是呈現研究成果的基本形式
So it's important to always report these effect sizes, but not just to report them,
報告效果量不只是論文寫作的必知事項
but also to correctly interpret them.
也要了解正確的解讀方式
Effect sizes serve three main goals.
呈現效果量有三大目標
First of all,
首先
they allow you to communicate the practical significance of the results.
作者可借此傳達研究操作的結果真正顯著之處
And effect might be statistically significant, but
儘管效果是統計顯著的
does it actually really matter in practice?
但真的是研究操作造成的嗎？
Second, effect sizes allow you to draw meta-analytic conclusions.
其二、效果量有助整合分析式結論的佈局
If there are a number of studies in the published literature, you can group all
只要收集同主題的出版文獻，
任何人都能整合並計算整合分析效果量
these studies together, calculate the meta-analytic effect size and
只要收集同主題的出版文獻，
任何人都能整合並計算整合分析效果量
get the best estimate of the true effect size in the population.
可估計來源母群的真實效果量
If we take a look at simulated studies where we perform independent t-tests and
拿這個獨立t檢定模擬研究來說
each group has 25 participants,
每一群有25人
you can see that there's quite a lot of variation in the effect size estimate.
這幅森林圖(forest plot)裡每個方塊代表一項研究結果
This forest plot illustrates effect sizes by the squares.
每個結果的平均值變異範圍很大
And you can see that the squares jump around a little bit on the xs and
最下面的菱形代表這些研究的整合效果量
the xs is the effect size.
So in this case there's actually no true effect size,
因為菱形落在數值0之上
there's no true effect in the population, so the true effect size is zero.
表示並沒有真實效果存在，所以效果量為0
But we've drawn random samples from this population and
圖中的所有研究是取自母群的隨機樣本
you can see that the effect size estimate within each individual sample actually
研究結果平均值有高有低
differs from quite reasonably high and quite reasonably low effect size estimate,
但是都與0相差不遠
even though the true estimate should be zero.
所以估計的效果量為0是合理的
Now finally effect sizes allow
you to perform a power analysis.
最後，效果量是檢定力分析的素材
When we talk about controlling type two errors,
上週談型二錯誤率控制的課程裡
it's important to think about what the true effect might be in the population.
提到了解真實效果的重要性
And an effect size tells you this, and you can use it in a power analysis to
有了效果量估計值，你可以用檢定力分析
determine the amount participants that the study would require to achieve
決定能成功發現真實效果的所需樣本數
a certain probability of finding a true effect if it's really there.
Now this is an example of G power, which is free software, and
這是G Power軟體的介面截圖
I'm not going to explain exactly how you should use it.
這段影片我不會詳述使用方法
We'll talk about this in an assignment.
本週作業有詳細的指引
I just want to highlight this field where you see that the effect size, Cohen's d,
只要注意這張圖的Effect size dz欄位
needs to be inserted if you want to perform the power calculations.
輸入數值就可以計算檢定力
There are different types of effect sizes.
效果量有許多種類
There are unstandardized effect sizes,
像是非標準化效果量
which are basically the difference that
you've observed between two groups.
就只是兩組之間的差異
Let's say you measure how quickly I can run down the corridor.
像是用碼錶測量人類的主觀計時
You measure how quickly someone else runs down the corridor.
就是到了指定秒數時，一個人能多快按錶
You do this multiple times and you want to see whether one or the other is fastest.
找兩個人做這個測試好幾次再來比較誰快
Now in this case, there's no need to calculate any weird type of effect size.
這個狀況不必計算任何奇怪的效果量
You can just use the time as an unstandardized effect size.
兩個人的時間差就是非標準化效果量
People all understand how to interpret time.
結果人人都看得懂
So time is a very logical skill to use, and
時間單位是有邏輯的單位
if I'm two seconds faster, you know how you should interpret this.
我說其中一人快了兩秒，你馬上就懂什麼意思
Now not all research allows you to used on standardized effect sizes.
可惜不是所有研究都適合用非標準化效果量
For example think about people in the literature who study happiness.
例如快樂感研究用的量表
They might measure happiness by asking people how happy are you at this moment.
有測量當下的快樂感的七點量表
Ranging from not happy at all at 1, to 7, very happy.
選項有1代表不快樂，到代表7快樂
Other people in the literature might use a five point scale to measure happiness.
也有研究者用五點量表測量快樂感
We can immediately see that the happiness score of 4 does not have any
所以4在這兩份量表示的意義並不相同
fixed meaning.
It really depends on the scale that was used.
解讀時要注意是那一版量表
So if you want to compare the size of the difference between these studies,
如果要比較不同研究的效果量差異
we need to find a way to standardized these differences.
就要把差異標準化
And that's what standardized effect size can do.
這就是需要標準化效果量的狀況
Now it's very important to interpret the effect size of a study.
現在談如何正確解讀效果量
A statistically significant effect alone might not be real reason to worry.
統計顯著與否並不是關鍵
And this is a good example.
我用這個例子說明
There was a study performed by Facebook which influenced how happy
這個研究展示什麼因素影響臉書使用者的快樂感受
people would feel.
The way that they did this was either by removing some very positive posts on
研究者的方法是移除使用者臉書頁面的
正面訊息或負面訊息
people's timelines or they removed very negative posts on people's timelines.
研究者的方法是移除使用者臉書頁面的
正面訊息或負面訊息
And then they measured the comments that people typed on Facebook and
然後測量使用者之後一段時間在臉書的留言正負面傾向
how positive or negative were the Facebook posts that people made.
Now it's quite a lot of attention for this study because the result show that when
這研究的吸睛之處是結果顯示
people saw less positive information, people actually were slightly
使用者看到較少的正面訊息
less positive in the Facebook messages that they post themselves.
個人留言也比較少正面訊息
Now if we look really at the data themselves and
不管報告的統計顯著，深入看資料細節的話
especially not on whether they were statistically significant or not, but
at the effect size, we can see that the effect size here was a Cohen's d of 0.001.
這個研究結果的Cohen's d只有0.001
Now that's a very tiny effect size.
是個非常微弱的效果量
It was statistically significant because Facebook has a huge amount of data.
結果是統計顯著是因為臉書有海量使用者
They have millions and millions of Facebook posts to analyze.
研究者分析的資料有「成億上兆」的臉書留言
But the difference that they observed was so small, that it was for
但是以實際效益來說，這樣的效果量並無任何意義
all practical purposes, almost meaningless.
This implies that the effect that they observed was so
這份報告呈現的資料集中於極少數的情緒性字詞的觀察
small in the emotional connotation of the words that
people typed that after 3,570 words, one more negative
像是使用者留言三千多個中性字詞後
word was typed in the condition where people did not see the positive feedback.
寫出一個負向字詞就歸類為「負面回應」
Now unless you type really,
除非使用者都在臉書寫很長的留言，
這樣的觀察很難反應個人行為
really long Facebook posts, this is not a noticeable effect at an individual level.
除非使用者都在臉書寫很長的留言，
這樣的觀察很難反映個別行為
This is only statistically significant over a huge number of people.
這種差異只有放在巨量資料才會呈現統計顯著
But people already worried, and there was even one
但這樣的研究結果會讓人聯想到
blog post somewhere where they said we know that mood is correlated with suicide.
只要有一個部落客散播有關自殺的訊息，
會不會就有影響
So maybe by experimenting on people,
若是利用臉書進行這種社會實驗
Facebook actually caused more people to commit suicide.
搞不好會引起自殺朝
But if you interpret the effect size, you can see that the effect is so, so
不過理解效果量的意義之後
tiny, that this is basically impossible to have real life consequences.
你會發現這對真實生活的影響非常微小
So it's important to think that effects might be statistically significant, but
研究發現的效果雖然有統計意義的顯著
they can be practically insignificant.
卻沒有現實意義的顯著
Just because there is a true effect doesn't mean that we need to care or
即使效果確實存在也不代表值得擔心
worry about it.
On the other hand, it's also important to realize
另一方面，理解能影響真實世界的微弱效果是很重要的
that small effects might have real world consequences.
In the meta-analysis in which researchers studied interventions for
像是有關青少年犯罪處置研究的整合性分析
juvenile delinquency, they found that these interventions had reliable but
顯示各類處置有些微但可信的效用
small effects size, Cohen's d of 0.11.
換算成Cohen's d是0.11
Now even though we consider this a small effect,
即使這些處置的效果微小
it has real life consequences that changes people's lives after the intervention.
依然能真正改變一些人的人生
Instead of 50% of the young people leaving jails going on to
因為這些處置讓青少年犯入監服刑的比例
commit more crimes, this reduces to about 45%.
從50%降到45%
So this might be a small difference, but it's a very impactful difference for
雖然整體數據改變不大，
卻帶給不少人不可估量的改變
these people.
雖然整體數據改變不大，
卻帶給不少人不可估量的改變
It's also important to interpret effect sizes because they can be
還需要知道的是效果量有可能是無法解釋的巨大
implausibly large.
We talked about small effect sizes maybe being not really practically relevant.
剛剛提到微小的效果量也許沒有實質意義
But big effects can also make you wonder what's really being studied and
巨大的效果量也會讓研究者懷疑原始問題
whether the result really makes sense.
以及結果是不是真有意義
Let's look at one example.
來看看這個例子
In this study, researchers found a correlation
這個研究報告白人的自殺率
between the suicide rate of white individuals and
the amount of country music that was played on the radio.
與電台播放鄉村音樂的相關性
Now this study won an award, an Ig Nobel prize, which is a prize for
作者因此獲得搞笑諾貝爾獎
studies that make you laugh and then make you think.
這個獎表揚讓人會心一笑又值得省思的研究
Now, in this case I think this study should make you think effect sizes,
我認為這個研究提醒研究者發現巨大的效果量時
and how implausibly large effect sizes might
要確定這項發現的可信度，而非僥倖
indicate that this is not a reliable effect, but just a fluke.
Indeed it turns out that follow up research was not able to confirm this
這種發現可能導致其他研究者難以重現
result.
And if you look at the effect size in this case,
這份報告的的效果量是相關係數
we can see that there's a correlation of .54, which is a large correlation.
作者報告.54，表示變項之間有相當高的相關
That's a sizeable, noticeable effect.
高到很容易讓人聯想
And it should make you wonder whether it's likely that listening to country music on
會好奇聽鄉村音樂真的會提高自殺率
the radio really has such a huge effect on the likelihood that people will commit
suicide.
會好奇聽鄉村音樂真的會提高自殺率
If you see an effect size this large you should say,
有概念的研究者會提醒自已
I don't think that it's very plausible.
變項間很難有實質關係
And you should make sure that you keep some doubts about the reliability of this
無論如何都要保持對這種發現的批判立場
finding.
There are two types of families of effect sizes.
效果量主要有兩大類
A differentiation is made between the Cohen's d family,
Cohen's d一類的效果量主要用來測量差異
which are standardized mean differences.
大多數是標準化平均值差異
And the other hand we have the r family,
另一類是相關係數
which are measures of strength of association, things like correlations.
用來測量變項之間的關聯強度
And then the next lectures, we'll go into more detail about both these families.
之後兩講會深入介紹這兩類效果量
Now in this lecture, we talked about the importance of reporting and
這一講談報告效果量的重要性
interpreting effect sizes.
還要解讀的必知要事
Effect sizes might arguably be the most important outcome of a study.
有人認為效果量是研究報告最重要的成份
The p value will tell you something about whether there's a signal or a noise.
p值指示研究能否真的偵測出效果
But even if there is noise, you might want to just accurately estimate that the true
即使偵測不到
還是可以用效果量估計真實為0的效果
effect is almost completely zero.
即使偵測不到
還是可以用效果量估計真實為0的效果
So you should always report effect
sizes in your results sections, and
任何研究者應在報告中呈現效果量
more importantly, you should also always
interpret the size of the effect.
更要仔細說明效果量的意義
[MUSIC]
影片結束